Sliding window is one of the most fun
patterns to solve. That is because you
can actually take up a data structure
like an array and then you can define a
window over it.
This window now has some elements. And
now you can slide this window throughout
your entire array.
I feel that this kind of keeps you
focused on the goal and it really
becomes interesting as well.
Let us find out more about it. Hello
friends, welcome back to my channel.
I feel that the name sliding window is
intuitive in itself. You have a window
that contains some elements and then you
are sliding this window. To understand
it better, let us immediately dive into
some problems. That will give you a very
good idea what this pattern is all
about. You might have already seen
problems of this pattern. You need to
find the maximum sum of a sub array of
size K.
You are given an array that even sorted
and you are given a value K. It means
you need to find me a sub array of size
K, that means four elements, such that
you have the maximum sum. So, what is
the brute force approach? You will try
to find out all of the sub array of size
four and then you will try to keep a
track of all of the sums.
But over here, what you can do is you
know that you have to look at four
elements at once
and they all should be contiguous.
This means you can apply the sliding
window over here.
Technically, what is going to happen is
you are trying to define a window that
contains four elements.
And if you look at these four elements,
you find that the total sum of these
elements is three, correct?
Now, you have to traverse other elements
as well.
For a brute force approach, you will try
to find out the other four elements.
But with a sliding window, what you can
do is you can simply take this window
and slide one step ahead.
Once you slide it, what did you do? You
added three, so you do a plus three, and
then you removed a minus two. So, you
remove minus two.
Now, you will get your new sum. And that
is eight.
So, this is how we are taking advantage
of a window that is sliding.
In the next step, what is going to
happen? You slide your window one step
ahead again.
So, what did we do? We added an eight,
and we removed a minus five.
So, now what do I get? I get the sum as
21.
This is what we are doing over here.
We take this window, and we slide it one
step at a time all throughout the array.
And that is why we call it a sliding
window pattern. You know that this size
is going to remain fixed,
or rather, you are talking about
elements that appear contiguous.
That is your very big indication.
So, now you know what to do, right? You
can keep on sliding this window
at every set of four elements, and just
keep a track of the sum of each of these
four elements.
Even this is easy. You just add the new
element, and remove the previous
element. That's it.
Just keep a track of all of these sums,
and in the end, you can return the
maximum sum that you found.
If you want to return that array, you
can keep a track of these four elements
also.
And that's it. You have found out the
answer.
You might have seen other problems like
this also. For example, in this one, you
have to find out the average instead of
the sum.
Do you really think it requires a whole
different implementation?
It is literally the same logic.
You take up your window, and then find
out the average.
And then, once you slide it, just add
the new element, remove the previous
one, and get a new average. Keep a track
of the average across your entire window
and once you reach the end, you can
stop. That's it. You solved one more
problem.
And sliding window is not just limited
to integers.
For example, in this problem, I need to
find out the maximum vowels in a
substring of size K.
Once again, all of these words are just
tweaked and asked in a different manner.
What do you have to do in this problem
in the end?
Once again, you are given a certain
size.
You know that you will have a substring
of this particular length of the size
four.
It means I will have a window of size
And once again, what do you need to do?
Just count how many vowels can you find?
For example, in this particular window,
you can only find one vowel.
Then you slide ahead, this time you have
two vowels.
Again, you slide ahead, again two
vowels. Again, you slide ahead, again
two vowels.
So, you just keep on scanning your
entire array like this
and at the very end, you can simply
return, "Okay, this is the maximum
number of vowels that I found." All I'm
trying to say is there are multiple ways
to ask the same question. Whereas, the
underlying idea about applying a sliding
window will remain the same. So, what
did we learn so far?
We understood how a sliding window
actually works and what is the intuition
behind it.
You are looking at some contiguous
elements and then you are sliding this
window all throughout your input array.
Now, there can be two different types of
sliding windows.
The problems that we just saw, they were
a fixed size of sliding window.
So, whenever you hear terms like do
something with K elements,
that means you are restricting that,
"Okay, I need to look at only these K
elements."
In those patterns, you will take up this
window and then you're going to slide it
one character at a time. When you slide
one character at a time or even faster,
it simply means that you are iterating
over your entire array.
You are able to perform a complete scan,
and that ensures that you have covered
every element.
Now, this is the most basic part how you
use a sliding window pattern.
There is, however, one more way in which
sliding window patterns are generally
used, and that is where things start to
get a little tricky. It means the length
of your sliding window can change.
We call this as a variable-size sliding
window pattern. The idea over here is
very simple. Let us say you're starting
off your window just with one element.
Now, based upon your problem statement,
what you may want to do is you may want
to cover more and more elements in your
array
until a certain condition is met.
So, you might have encountered questions
like, "Okay, find me the array that has
K distinct characters."
It means you are looking for some
particular K characters.
Now, it could be possible that all the
characters are repeated. So, you're
continuing to increase the length of
your sliding window until you find those
distinct characters.
Or you could even use hash sets or even
some kind of a frequency map to keep a
track of those K elements.
So, whenever you're hearing terms like
at most K characters,
it means you need the concept of a
variable-size sliding window.
For example, you covered certain
elements. But now, when you want to
cover your entire array,
sometimes you may have to remove some
elements from your window.
So, what you will do is you will start
reducing the length, and it could be
possible that you may want to include
more characters. All of this happens
dynamically as per your requirements.
It could be possible that after several
iterations, you have now covered your
entire array.
All of this isn't very, very complex.
Let us look at some problems that will
make this concept even more clear to
you. For example, look at this
particular problem.
You need to find me the longest
substring without any repeating
character.
I have this entire string with me.
And you need to give me a substring in
which none of the characters are
repeated, but the length should be
maximum.
So, you can find several of these
strings, right?
In all these strings, none of the
characters are repeated. But if you take
this particular string,
this I now gets repeated.
So, this is where you stop.
For a brute-force approach, you will try
to now start with H, then you will try
to start with I, and so on.
The time complexity is going to get
worse and worse.
How does the sliding window help over
here?
You start with the first element. You
see, okay, currently no character is
repeating here.
Then you include one more character.
Once again, no character is repeated.
What you can also do is you can keep
these characters in some kind of a hash
set, so you can easily find out if a
character got repeated or not.
You will continue ahead. You see I, I is
also not present. You see S,
S is also not present, and now you see
an I again.
What happens? This I is repeated, so you
will not include it in your window,
but you found a checkpoint. You found
that, "Okay, I can find one string of
the length four which doesn't have any
repeated characters."
So, this is one benchmark. When you have
to go ahead, what will you do?
You will now try to
add a character.
I got added,
but since it is duplicated, you will
want to keep on removing characters
until your sliding window have unique
characters again.
So, I will keep on removing until I
don't have any duplicates. I still have
two eyes. I remove this. I still have
two eyes. I remove this. And now I only
have one eye.
All the elements are again unique. But
this time the length is two.
Since two is less than four, so I can
ignore it.
You will try to repeat the same process
again. You add an S.
So, now you have a repeated characters.
So, you will reduce the length of your
window.
You will go ahead now. You find A.
None of them are repeated.
L, none of them are repeated. O, none of
them are repeated. N, none of them are
repeated. Then G and then a X.
What did we do? We covered the entire
string and none of the characters are
repeated. So, what did we find out? We
find out that the longest substring
without any repeated characters is
actually eight.
And we were using the concept of of a
variable size sliding window.
The window was sliding, but its length
was not fixed.
And that is your answer.
But these problems can start to become
more and more generalized and they might
feel a little bit more tricky.
But you don't have to worry about it.
Just focus on your basics and everything
will be fine.
For example, look at this next problem.
You have to find out the longest
substring with at most K distinct
characters.
So, the underlying idea will still
remain the same. You will want to have a
variable size sliding window.
But just looking at repeated characters
isn't enough.
You will also want to make sure that the
string that you're forming
this string should have at most K
distinct characters.
For example, in the previous question,
as soon as I got an I, then I had to
started to reduce the length.
But over here, I am good with at most K
distinct characters.
So, if I try to add one more element,
how many distinct characters do I have?
I still have only four distinct
characters.
So, this window works perfectly for me.
Can I go ahead? Yes, I can.
Because, even now, I only have four
distinct characters.
But, can I go ahead now?
As soon as I included A, I now have five
distinct characters. So, this is an
indication that you need to start
reducing your length.
So, what will you do? You'll try to cut
off one element. Now, again, you have
four elements, so that works
wonderfully.
Now, go ahead.
Once again, you have five distinct
characters, so you will need to reduce
your length.
Similarly, you will keep on going ahead.
You include an O. Now, again, you have
five characters, so remove this.
Notice that, if you removed an I, you
still have five distinct characters. So,
you need to reduce the length even more.
When you removed an S, you still have
five distinct characters. So, you need
to remove more characters.
And that happened because these
characters were duplicated, correct?
So, that is the idea.
Now, once again, you have four distinct
characters, so this also becomes a
candidate.
Similarly, you would keep on scanning
your entire string, and that will cover
every element. But, you have already
found out that the longest string with
at most four distinct characters is this
particular substring.
You might have guessed it. The problem
statement is actually the same.
You are just playing around with all of
the different conditions that could be
asked.
So, basically, how do you identify that,
when you're given a problem, can you
apply the sliding window pattern or not?
There are certain cues that you can
watch out for.
For example, the first thing that you
need to look at is a linear structure.
Sliding window only operates when your
structure is linear. You cannot use it
on trees or graphs.
So, arrays and strings are perfect
examples because all of these elements
are contiguous and then you can have a
window on top of it. That means you're
looking at only certain set of elements.
And that is why a contiguous segment is
very, very important. Because notice
what we demanded in all of our problems.
We were looking at sub-arrays,
sub-strings, a part of the string, a
part of an array.
Those are your major hints.
And notice what the problem asks you
for.
Find the minimum and the maximum. That
means you're looking at a window and you
have to tell me, "Okay, this is the
maximum size or this is the minimum
size."
Count distinct or duplicates. You are
maintaining a hash fit to find distinct
elements. You are also maintaining a
hash fit to find duplicates. You could
also maintain frequency maps. That is
giving you a state of what is happening
in your window.
Basically, this window is your area of
concern. You're trying to derive all of
the results that you can find from this
window.
Let us now look at one fancy problem.
You might have all seen the problem
fruits into basket. Basically, you are
given an array that is certainly a
garden and all of the fruits are in a
line.
You're given a basket and this basket
can hold only two type of fruits.
You have to make sure that whichever two
type of fruits you pick,
you need to have the maximum quantity of
it.
And all of these fruits are contiguous.
So, what do you see over here?
Isn't this problem literally the same as
finding the longest sub-string with at
most K distinct characters?
What do you do? You start picking up
fruits. You pick up an apple and then
you pick up an orange.
You found two type of fruits. That's it,
and that's good.
So, you record it. Now, you try to pick
a watermelon.
You cannot have three types. So, you
will want to reduce your window.
This is perfect.
Now, try to add more fruits. Can you add
a watermelon? Yes.
So, now you are able to add
three fruits. So, that is a bigger
number.
Works perfectly.
Try to add the next fruit. Can I add a
banana? No, because now I will have
three type of fruits. So, remove the
orange,
and this is a good for us.
I still have three fruits, so I don't
need to update it.
Try to add the next fruit. Can I add an
orange? No, because now I will have
three different kind of fruits.
It means I will need to reduce my size.
Reducing the size by one does not help.
I still have three different fruits.
Remove one more fruit.
I again have only two type of fruits, so
that is good.
I can now increase. Can I add one more
orange? Yes.
Can I add an apple? No.
So, I will reduce it.
Notice that I was still able to have
only three maximum fruits.
Can I add an orange again? Yes, because
once again, in my basket, I only have
two type of fruits. But, the total
fruits I collected over here is four.
Four is greater than three, so I will
reject this value. I have scanned my
entire array. That means four is my
answer.
So, do you see how sliding window is
helping us? It helps to scan the entire
array. It removes the order of n squared
complexity. It helps you to focus only
on a certain state of elements, and you
are maintaining that state.
Up till now, we have been looking at the
maximum substring, the maximum number of
fruits. Similarly, you can also have a
problem where you have to find the
minimum size of a sub array with a
particular sum.
You are given this array, and you have
to find the target of seven as the sum.
So, what do you do? Again, a variable
size sliding window. You take up the
first element. The sum is two. It is
less than seven, so you don't have to
worry.
You do 2 + 3.
It is still five. So, it is still
smaller. I add one more element.
The sum is six.
Still less than seven.
And now I add one more element. The
total sum now becomes eight.
And what is the length of this array?
The length is four.
So, at least I found out one possible
solution. But until I scan my entire
array, then I am not sure.
So, what are you basically doing over
here? This is the left pointer and this
is the right pointer.
To increase your length, you do a right
plus plus and to decrease your length,
you do a left minus minus.
So, what I will do over here? I will do
a left minus minus.
What is my sum now?
My sum is six.
It is less than seven, so I will need to
increase my right pointer to increase
the sum.
So, when I'm increasing the size of my
window, my sum increases. When I'm
decreasing the size of the window, the
sum decreases. I add the next element
and now the sum becomes 10.
10 is greater than seven. So, this is a
possible solution. But I can also now
start to reduce my size.
I see 4 + 2 6 + 1 7, so I found an even
smaller size.
That is three.
Can I reduce it further? No, because now
the sum becomes six.
I try to add one more element.
The sum now becomes nine. So, I found
one more answer. But I can also try to
reduce it. So, when I reduce it, my sum
is still seven. So, I found an even
smaller solution. So, I will update this
value to two. I have scanned my entire
array. That means two is my answer. So,
a sliding window is also helpful when
you have to find the minimum of
something.
The next problem is also very very
interesting, maximum consecutive ones.
You are given a binary array, that means
just zeros and ones, and you are given a
value K.
What you can do is you can pick up at
most two zeros to convert it to one.
And these zeros could be anywhere in the
array.
And then you have to tell me what is the
longest length of all ones that you can
find out.
So, what do you do over here? Once
again, a variable size sliding window.
You have to find out the ones, correct?
So, start your window.
Currently, you haven't flipped any of
the zeros. That's good.
Now, increase the length. This is good.
Increase the length, that is good. Now,
increase the length.
What do I have? I have a zero.
I haven't used any of this. So, what I'm
just going to do is I will change this K
to one.
And notice, my left pointer is here, my
right pointer is here.
I will try to increase the length more
because I'm still allowed to flip one
more zero.
My right pointer comes here, and this
value now changes to zero. It means I
cannot flip any more zeros.
So, what happens if I try to go ahead
now? If I try to go ahead, I cannot flip
the zero.
So, I actually need to stop over here.
And this gives me one particular length.
I now know that
I can have at least five consecutive
ones.
This fact is known.
I still have to scan my entire array.
Notice that I couldn't have included
this array. Why? Because the value of K
is zero.
So, I will start reducing my length. I
reduce this, but this was not a zero.
So, the value of K still remains a zero.
I remove one more one, no change. I
remove one more one, no change. I remove
the zero.
Since I removed a zero, my this value of
K now changes to one.
It means I can include one more zero.
As soon as I include a zero,
the value of K now changes to zero
again.
It means I cannot include more zeros.
But I still want to keep on going ahead.
That is only I will know if I have more
zeros or ones.
I see a one, that is fine.
So, you keep on going ahead until you
see a one.
So, what do we have now? We have another
window of a greater size. This window is
of the size six. So, I can update it and
I can store six is my longest length up
till now.
Can I include the next zero? No. So, I
need to move my left pointer one step
ahead.
This pointer moves ahead, the size of
the window reduces,
and now I'm able to ingest one more
zero.
The length, however, still remains six.
I have completed the scan of my entire
array. I found out that, okay, six is
the maximum length of maximum
consecutive ones.
All of these examples give you a good
summary about the components involved in
a variable-size sliding window.
The idea is very, very simple. If you
want to expand your window, then you
take up your two pointers and then you
do a right plus plus.
So, I have my two pointers over here.
Doing a right plus plus will increase
the size of my window.
And I have included more elements.
Based upon your conditions, you might
want to shrink your window also.
So, you do left plus plus. You had your
window like this. You have a left
pointer and a right pointer. When you do
left plus plus, your window size becomes
smaller.
Basically, you are trying to maintain
the state. You are trying to maintain
the particular condition that is being
asked in your problem statement. So, you
are trying to validate if your window
valid or not? And based upon that, you
are increasing the length of your window
or reducing the length.
To maintain this state, you can use a
hash set, a running sum, a frequency
map, or min and max queues.
And while you're doing all of this, you
need to make sure that you reach the
very end of your array. It means you
have completed the entire scan.
And while doing all of that, you might
want to update a counter, you might want
to keep some kind of a track.
It just means that you are trying to
update the end result that will
eventually solve the problem for you.
So, what did we learn over here? You
need to somehow look at the problem and
identify the sliding window opportunity.
For example, whenever you're being
talked about a contiguous sub array or a
longest or a shortest segment,
it means that you want to look at
different sizes.
It simply means you're looking at a
variable-size sliding window.
When you're being talked about the
maximum sum or a minimum value between
certain key elements, it means you're
looking at a fixed-size sliding window.
If you're looking at at most key
elements, then you want the minimum
possible sum. You want the minimum
possible elements. It means a shrinking
window strategy. Meaning, you will try
to include more and more elements and
then try to shrink it as per your
requirement, as per the condition that
you want to meet. And likewise, we also
discussed the other two cases. If you're
looking at unique elements, that means
you might want to use a hash set or a
hash map. And looking at moving averages
or rolling sums, those are once again
fixed window where you're updating your
result.
I hope all of these problems now give
you a very good idea how the sliding
window pattern actually looks and in
what scenarios can you apply it.
Tell me in the comment section below
what other problems have you seen or
what other complex cases you that you
have observed where a sliding window
pattern is very very helpful. I will be
really happy to discuss all of them and
it will also become a very good
collection whenever you want to review
this particular concept.
As a reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated and I can make more such
videos. Also, remember you can now
schedule one-to-one sessions with me to
solve any sort of doubts. And also a
huge shout-out to all of the members who
support my channel. You guys really keep
me going and as a member, you do get
priority reply to your comments and
early access to new videos as well. Stay
tuned for my upcoming video. Until then,
see you.